Alfred Diamant papers, 1950-2010 C565
Indiana University Archives
Alfred Diamant papers
1950-2010
1960-1996
Indiana University Archives
Diamant, Alfred, 1917-2012
C565
6.4 cubic feet 7 boxes
Alfred Diamant was a professor of Political Science at Indiana University from 1967 to 1988 and served as the Chair of Political Science and West European Studies. He taught all levels of political science from introductory to doctoral courses with a special interest in comparative government. This collection consists of Diamant's academic papers including class material, student correspondence, and personal publications.
Access Restrictions
Select files are closed to researchers.
Advance notice required for access to this collection.
Biographical Note
Born September 25, 1917 in Vienna, Austria, Alfred "Freddy" Diamant escaped religious persecution in 1940 and settled in the United States. After the attack on Pearl Harbor, Diamant could not enlist, but was drafted by the United States military to fight for the cause of the Allies. After volunteering to speed up his service, he started basic training at Fort Knox, Kentucky and was later transferred to Fort Benjamin Harrison in Indianapolis, Indiana. He was selected for Officers Graduate School and served in Maryland. There, his commanders learned of his German speaking skills and he was trained as an interrogator of prisoners of war for three months. Before being sent to England in 1944, Diamant became an American citizen.
On D-Day, June 6, 1944, Diamant served as part of the 82nd Airborne Division. His team was dropped eighteen miles off course. He was fortunate to survive, but was captured and taken as a prisoner of war. After attempting to escape, Diamant was shot in the back by his pursuers and survived a potentially fatal shot. He and the other prisoners were rescued in the following days. His wound was enough to send him home where he enrolled at Indiana University and pursued his interest in political science.
He achieved two degrees in political science at Indiana University in 1947 and obtained his Ph.D. from Yale in 1957. He taught at the University of Florida (1950-1960), Haverford College (1960-1967), and finally, Indiana University, from which he retired in 1988. During his tenure at IU he served as the Chair of Political Science and the Chair of West European Studies. Over the course of his career, Diamant earned various prestigious awards, including the Guggenheim in 1973 and a Fulbright Senior Research Fellowship. He was described by his colleagues and students as a tenacious, courteous, and intellectual person who had a keen interest in both his students and colleagues. He married his wife Ann Redmon Diamant in 1943 and the couple had two children, Alice and Steve. He passed away on May 11, 2012.
Arrangement
Collection is organized into two series: Teaching files and Publications
Scope and Content Note
This collection houses Diamant's academic contributions. The main series of Teaching files (1950-1996) include his teaching and class material, student correspondence, the second contains his publications (1954-2010). The files in the Student correspondence sub-series includes a large number of recommendation letters. As such, the sub-series is closed but may be made available with advance notice so that the Archivist may review the specific files requested.
This collection spans the time period between 1950 and 2010 (when his memoir was published). Other related materials containing information regarding his personal life can be found in the Lilly Library (Diamant mss).
Related Material
Additional publications and research materials may be accessed in IUScholarworks: http://scholarworks.iu.edu/
Related photographs may be available in the University Archives Photographs Database: http://webapp1.dlib.indiana.edu/archivesphotos/
Acquisition Information
Accession 2013/088, 2014/062
Provenance
Given to the University Archives by Alice Diamant, Alfred Diamant's daughter, in 2013 and 2014.
Appraisal
Records removed from this collection include student grades. Student final grades can be found at the Office of the Registrar.
Political science --Study and teaching (Higher) --Indiana --Bloomoington --History --20th century --Sources; Political scientists --Indiana --Bloomoington --History --20th century --Sources; Indiana University, Bloomington. Department of Political Science -- Faculty -- Archives; Indiana University. Department of Political Science -- Faculty -- Archives; Diamant, Alfred, 1917-2012 -- Archives; Diamant, Alfred, 1917-2012 -- Correspondence
- Teaching files, 1950-1996 (Box 1)
  - Course materials, 1950-1995
    - Additional Materials, 1994-1995 (Box 1)
    - Berlin Guide, 1984 (Box 1)
    - Comparative Government – Haverford College, Columbia, 1961-1965 (Box 1)
    - Comparative Politics Exams (Qualifying Exams), 1969-1989 (Box 1)
    - Comparative Politics (University of Florida) (Box 1)
      - Grad Syllabi/Exams (University of Florida), 1959-1960 (Box 1)
      - Undergraduate Syllabi, 1950-1983 (Box 1)
    - Hand-outs, 1994-1995 (Box 1)
    - Miscellaneous Courses, 1967-1973 (Box 1)
    - Political Theory – Haverford College, Syllabi, 1963-1983 (Box 1)
    - W605/Y657 (Box 1)
      - Notes I, 1983-1989 (Box 1)
      - Notes II, 1983-1989 (Box 1)
      - Notes II Germany, 1983-1989 (Box 1)
      - Notes III, undated (Box 1)
    - Y103 American Politics, 1981-1987 (Box 1)
    - Y210 Holocaust (Box 1)
      - Lectures, 1983-1988 (Box 1)
      - Exams, Syllabi, 1983-1988 (Box 1)
    - Y335 (Box 1)
      - Notes I, II, 1974-1975 (Box 1)
      - Formal/Informal, 1974-1975 (Box 1)
      - Syllabi, 1967-1988 (Box 1)
    - Y396 Democracy (Box 1)
      - Notes, 1980 (Box 1)
      - Exams, Syllabi, 1980-1986 (Box 1)
    - Y570 Diamant/Gillespie, 1970-1971 (Box 1)
    - Y657 (Box 1)
      - A/I Syllabi/Exams, 1983-1989 (Box 1)
      - A/I Notes I, 1983-1989 (Box 1)
      - A/I Notes II, 1983-1989 (Box 1)
      - Exams, worksheets, 1968-1994 (Box 1)
      - Syllabi, 1965-1995 (Box 1)
  - Student Correspondence, 1952-1996
    Access Restrictions
    This entire series is closed to researchers at this time. Files are housed in boxes 3-7.
    General
    The files in the Student correspondence sub-series includes a large number of recommendation letters. As such, the sub-series is closed but may be made available with advance notice so that the Archivist may review the specific files requested.
    - Recommendations (Box 1)
      - A-B, 1957-1994 (Box 1)
      - C-E, 1954-1991 (Box 1)
      - F-G, 1956-1991 (Box 1)
      - Hetzner, Candace, 1989 (Box 1)
      - H, 1959-1991 (Box 1)
      - I-K, 1955-1995 (Box 1)
      - L-M, 1954-1994 (Box 1)
      - N-R, 1952-1989 (Box 1)
      - Schmidt, Vivien-Ann, 1991-1992 (Box 1)
      - Sa-Sh, 1961-1985 (Box 1)
      - Si-Sz, 1957-1989 (Box 1)
      - T-Z, 1957-1988 (Box 1)
    - Abdelrahman, A. Abdelrahman, 1970-1975 (Box 1)
    - Abshire, Jean, 1991-1998 (Box 1)
    - Al-Sohaibani, Abdolrahman, 1987-1989 (Box 1)
    - Allen, Barbara, 1977-1989 (Box 1)
    - Allen, Pamela, 1984 (Box 1)
    - Austin, Joe, 1981-1982 (Box 1)
    - Backoff, Robert, 1976 (Box 1)
    - Ballard, Chris, 1984-1985 (Box 1)
    - Bendix, John, 1984-1996 (Box 1)
    - Barbour, Christie, 1980-1989 (Box 1)
    - Bova, Russ, 1981-1985 (Box 1)
    - Brady, Janet, 1977-1984 (Box 1)
    - Brown, Melissa, 1992 (Box 1)
    - Burns, Mark, 1975 (Box 1)
    - Carter, Paul, 1984-1996 (Box 1)
    - Casavina, Paul, 1972-1973 (Box 1)
    - Champagne, Rick, 1983-1986 (Box 1)
    - Cheung, Peter, 1984 (Box 1)
    - Chindalak, Vadhanasindhu, 1981-1988 (Box 1)
    - Choi, Y.H., 1971-1986 (Box 1)
    - Chung, Moo-Kwon, 1985-1995 (Box 1)
    - Comedy, Yolanda, 1989-1994 (Box 1)
    - Cox, Robert H., 1986-1995 (Box 1)
    - Craine, Richard, 1986-1989 (Box 1)
    - Cullather, Nicholas, 1980 (Box 1)
    - Cuzan, Alfred, 1972-1978 (Box 1)
    - Daigle, Steven, 1969-1970 (Box 1)
    - DeBruyn, Maria, 1972 (Box 1)
    - Deschamps, Elaine, 1994 (Box 1)
    - Dexheimer, Wolfgang, 1969-1983 (Box 1)
    - Diaconoff, Peter, 1967-1969 (Box 1)
    - Dillon, Peter, 1990 (Box 1)
    - di Geronimo, Victor, 1977-1982 (Box 1)
    - Dinse, John, 1970-1976 (Box 1)
    - Dodson, J. Michael, 1972-1977 (Box 1)
    - Eidlin, Fred, 1968-1970 (Box 1)
    - Ennenga, Wilma, 1982-1987 (Box 1)
    - Fairlie, Lyndell, 1970-1973 (Box 1)
    - Jose Carlos Fajardo, 1970-1980 (Box 1)
    - Fernandez, Jean Marc, 1977-1978 (Box 1)
    - Fitzgerald, Don, 1970-1977 (Box 1)
    - Fitzgerald, Keith, 1984-1989 (Box 1)
    - Flanders, Steven, 1968-1972 (Box 1)
    - Fornerino, Marines, 1993-1995 (Box 1)
    - Gill, Michael, 1971-1986 (Box 1)
    - Goehlert, Robert, 1977-1981 (Box 1)
    - Goodfellow, Sam, 1992-1993 (Box 1)
    - Golino, Louis R., 1984-1989 (Box 1)
    - Goran, George, 1970-1973 (Box 1)
    - Green, Barbara, 1969-1977 (Box 1)
    - Groelsema, Robert J., 1990-1995 (Box 1)
    - Guicherd, Catherine, 1983-1995 (Box 1)
    - Hadjikyriacou, Andreas, 1988 (Box 1)
    - Hamadi, Abdulkarim, 1976-1979 (Box 1)
    - Hansen, Emanuel, 1971-1973 (Box 1)
    - Hastedt, Glenn, 1975-1980 (Box 1)
    - Hayes, Lynton, 1970 (Box 1)
    - Hayes, Margaret, 1969-1975 (Box 1)
    - Hayes, Richard, 1969-1971 (Box 1)
    - Hersch, Gisela, 1968-1977 (Box 1)
    - Hetzner, Candace, 1976-1992 (Box 1)
    - Hiskes, Richard, 1975-1976 (Box 1)
    - Hudson, George E., 1969-1972 (Box 1)
    - Hume, Rex, 1971-1976 (Box 1)
    - Jang, Guhn-Choow, 1986 (Box 1)
    - Jansen, Alf-Inge, 1969 (Box 1)
    - Janzen, Eileen, 1978-1991 (Box 1)
    - Job, Brian, 1970 (Box 1)
    - Jogerst, Michael, 1968-1970 (Box 1)
    - Kahn, Beverly (Mrs.), 1974-1983 (Box 1)
    - Kahn, Robert, 1972-1978 (Box 1)
    - Kamenitsa, Lynn, 1990-1992 (Box 1)
    - Kangas, Roger, 1993 (Box 1)
    - Kay, Woodie, 1981-1987 (Box 1)
    - Kennedy, Ellen, 1985-1988 (Box 1)
    - Kessler, Christian, 1972-1974 (Box 1)
    - Kim, Jai-Hyup, 1971 (Box 1)
    - Young-Pyoung, Kim, 1978-1982 (Box 1)
    - Kukainis, Beate, 1970-1982 (Box 1)
    - Lois Kuter, 1979-1985 (Box 1)
    - Kyzer-Sheely, Gary, 1976-1977 (Box 1)
    - La, Jea Miw, 1969-1981 (Box 1)
    - Lawther, Wendell, 1971-1979 (Box 1)
    - Leal, Raymund R., 1975-1983 (Box 1)
    - Le Prestre, Philip, 1977-1986 (Box 1)
    - Lovell, Allen, 1986 (Box 1)
    - Loveman, Brian, 1969-1973 (Box 1)
    - Magnuson, Richard Axel, 1971-1981 (Box 1)
    - Malloy, Michael, 1989-1997 (Box 1)
    - Malloy, Michael II, 1994-1996 (Box 1)
    - Mark Mandeles, 1979-1986 (Box 1)
    - Mangun, William, 1974-1977 (Box 1)
    - Martin, James, 1978 (Box 1)
    - Matiko, Julius, 1968-1973 (Box 1)
    - McDavid, James, 1971-1975 (Box 1)
    - McMane, Aralynn Abare, 1987-1989 (Box 1)
    - Meeks, Margot, 1979-1980 (Box 1)
    - Meister, Kyle, 1986 (Box 1)
    - Meredith, Samuel, 1972-1978 (Box 1)
    - Michalak, Thomas, 1973 (Box 1)
    - Machels, Marcia, 1970-1981 (Box 1)
    - Michelmann, Hans, 1970-1992 (Box 1)
    - Michelmann, 1973-1975 (Box 1)
    - Michelson, Lorna, 1973 (Box 1)
    - Milakovich, Mike, 1969-1970 (Box 1)
    - Mitchell, Albert, 1969 (Box 1)
    - Mitchell, Michael, 1968-1977 (Box 1)
    - Mitchell, Neil, 1979-1987 (Box 1)
    - Molse, Lester, 1970-1974 (Box 1)
    - Mononi, Faustin-Emery, 1971-1973 (Box 1)
    - Morgado, Michael, 1975-1976 (Box 1)
    - Mueller, James, 1970-1971 (Box 1)
    - Murphy, Roger, 1990-1994 (Box 1)
    - Murray, Arlo Michael, 1969-1976 (Box 1)
    - Mushaben, J., 1969-1976 (Box 1)
    - Mushaben, Joyce, 1976-1988 (Box 1)
    - Nakhnikian, Ellen, 1970-1972 (Box 1)
    - Ndegwa, Steve, 1991-1992 (Box 1)
    - Nebert, D, 1972-1978 (Box 1)
    - Nicoll, Nancy L., 1983-1990 (Box 1)
    - Nulens, H.-G., 1980-1982 (Box 1)
    - Olander, Joseph D., 1969-1970 (Box 1)
    - Olguin, John, 1974-1989 (Box 1)
    - O'Shaughnessy, Laura, 1969-1977 (Box 1)
    - Olivo, Christiane, 1992-1996 (Box 1)
    - Quirk Miller, Nancy, 1983 (Box 1)
    - Pawinski, Monica, 1985-1986 (Box 1)
    - Peterson, James, 1976-1980 (Box 1)
    - Pickering, Jeff, 1991-1994 (Box 1)
    - Piecewicz, Richard W., 1978 (Box 1)
    - Porter, Vicki, 1984 (Box 1)
    - Postbrief, 1971-1973 (Box 1)
    - Puckett, Robert H., 1983 (Box 1)
    - Price, Barry, 1977-1989 (Box 1)
    - Rector, Henry, 1984-1990 (Box 1)
    - Reid, Phyllis Ann, 1969-1970 (Box 1)
    - Reynolds, John F., 1970-1971 (Box 1)
    - Richardson, Gregg, 1971 (Box 1)
    - Robertson, Dave, 1977-1986 (Box 1)
    - Rogers, Bruce, 1972 (Box 1)
    - Roll, Charles R., 1972-1976 (Box 1)
    - Rossow, Robert, 1971-1993 (Box 1)
    - Sabetti, Phillip, 1970-1982 (Box 1)
    - Salert, Barbara, 1972-1973 (Box 1)
    - Sanjian/Stephenson, Andrea, 1978-1983 (Box 1)
    - Sarti, Odile C (PhD Hist), 1983 (Box 1)
    - Scheffler, Pamela, 1985 (Box 1)
    - Sattinger, Gerald, 1968-1975 (Box 1)
    - Schmidt, David, 1976-1982 (Box 1)
    - Scheinman, Marc, 1970-1973 (Box 1)
    - Schneider, Peter, 1971-1973 (Box 1)
    - Schwarz, Gabriella, 1982-1985 (Box 1)
    - Scott, Eric Jon, 1971 (Box 1)
    - Shimkin, Alexander, undated (Box 1)
    - Simmons, James R., 1983 (Box 1)
    - Smedberg, Roblyn, 1980-1985 (Box 1)
    - Smith, Gordon Budd, 1973-1977 (Box 1)
    - Smith, James, 1976-1985 (Box 1)
    - Smith, Stuart M., 1988 (Box 1)
    - Staab, Andrew Westma, 1984-1985 (Box 1)
    - Staab, Eric P., 1990-1991 (Box 1)
    - Starks, Warren, 1975-1976 (Box 1)
    - Stein, George, 1969-1971 (Box 1)
    - Studlar, Donley, 1970-1980 (Box 1)
    - Thompson, Pamela, 1976-1977 (Box 1)
    - Trousdell, Elizabeth, 1984-1995 (Box 1)
    - Tunsiri, Vichai, 1969-1971 (Box 1)
    - Townsend, Allan, 1970-1977 (Box 1)
    - Ullman, Uri, 1977-1987 (Box 1)
    - Uslaner, Eric, 1971-1975 (Box 1)
    - Valentine, Shawna, 1985 (Box 1)
    - Valyocsik, Sander C., 1993-1995 (Box 1)
    - Votruba, Brian, 1994 (Box 1)
    - Walshok, Marko, 1968-1973 (Box 1)
    - Waltman, Jerrold, 1972-1990 (Box 1)
    - Wells, Margaret, 1971-1972 (Box 1)
    - West, Darrell, 1977-1984 (Box 1)
    - Whitaker, Gordon, 1970-1975 (Box 1)
    - White, Robert, 1971-1974 (Box 1)
    - Wildermuth, M., 1985 (Box 1)
    - Williams, Margit B., 1991-1996 (Box 1)
    - Wilson, Jeanne L., 1977-1983 (Box 1)
    - Wilz, Thomas, 1986 (Box 1)
    - Wright, George, 1974-1977 (Box 1)
    - Wright, Kristie, 1987 (Box 1)
    - Wynne, Susan, 1988 (Box 1)
    - Yahya, Ali, 1976-1979 (Box 1)
    - Zatlin, Dayle, 1972-1975 (Box 1)
    - Zulauf, Barry, 1982-1984 (Box 1)
- Publications and presentations, 1954-2010
  - "The Department, The Prefect, and Dual Supervision in French Administration: A Comparative Study", 1954 (Box 1)
  - "The Need for Local Government Reform in the United States", 1956 (Box 1)
  - "Austrian Catholics and the First Republic, 1918-1934: A Study in Anti-Democratic Thought", 1957 (Box 1)
  - "A Case Study of Administrative Autonomy: Controls and Tensions in French Administration", 1958 (Box 1)
  - "Austrian Catholics and the Social Question, 1918-1933", 1959 (Box 1)
  - "Bureaucracy in Western Europe", 1959 (Box 1)
  - Austrian Catholics and the First Republic: Democracy, Capitalism, and the Social Order, 1918-1934; 1960 (Box 2)
  - I Cattolici Austriaci e la Prima Repubblica, 1918-1934; 1964 (Box 2)
  - "The Comparative Study of Political Systems", 1964 (Box 2)
  - "European Models of Bureaucracy and Development", 1966 (Box 2)
  - "Verwaltung und Entwicklung: Wissenschaftliche Forschungstendenzen und Modelle in den USA", 1966 (Box 2)
  - "Political Development: Approaches to Theory and Strategy in Approaches to Development: Politics, Administration and Change", 1966 (Box 2)
  - Review of The Citizen and the Administrator in a Developing Democracy, 1968 (Box 2)
  - "Tradition and Innovation in French Administration", 1968; (French and English copies) (Box 2)
  - Measuring National Bureaucracies: The Interaction of Theory and Research, 1969 (Box 2)
  - Anti-Bureaucratic Utopias in Highly Industrialized Societies: A Preliminary Assessment, 1972 (Box 2)
  - Sozialstruktur und Politik in Frankreich, Chapter 5, 1976 (Box 2)
  - Democratizing the Workplace: The Myth and Reality of Mitbestimmung in the Federal Republic of Germany in Worker Self-Management in Industry: The West European Experience, 1977 (Box 2)
  - Worlds Apart, Worlds United: A European-American Story, The Memoirs of Ann & Alfred Diamant, 2010 (Box 2)
    (includes DVD of presentation given on same at the IU Emeriti House, 28 March 2011)
  - Box 3-7 Restricted (See above note) (Box 2)
  - Recommendations – Ballard (Box 3)
  - Barbour – Goran (Box 4)
  - Green – McDavid (Box 5)
  - McMane – Robertson (Box 6)
  - Rogers - Zulauf (Box 7)